Finding Aid for Charles Stuart Kennedy papers, ca. 1900-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Stuart Kennedy papers circa 1900-1966, 1937-1961
Kennedy, Charles Stuart, 1887-1966.
1 oversize folder
13 linear feet
851596 Aa 2
Detroit, Michigan physician and member of the University of Michigan Board of Regents, 1946-1961. Reports, correspondence, and agendas of meetings of the Board of Regents, the Workers Education Service, the American College of Surgeons and World War II; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated by Dr. Kennedy (donor no. 3921) in 1962; a smaller amount came from Charles S. Kennedy III (donor no. 9151 ) and another addition was made by Mary McCaughey (Donor No. 11004 ) in 2013.
No further additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Charles Stuart Kennedy was born in Detroit, Michigan on October 25, 1887. He received his B.S. in 1911 and his M.D. in 1913, both from the University of Michigan. Afterwards he returned to Detroit to become an assistant surgeon to his father, J.B. Kennedy. During World War I he served as first lieutenant at Base Hospital No. 11 in New Jersey, doing brain and peripheral nerve surgery. He then became Chief of Surgery and Chief of Medical Staff at Grace Hospital, as well as a consultant in surgery at a number of other Detroit hospitals. In 1941 he began teaching at Wayne State University and he also became a lecturer for post-graduates in surgery at the University of Michigan. He was one of the founders of the American Board of Surgery and served as Governor of the American College of Surgeons. He was also elected as regent of the University of Michigan in 1945, re-elected in 1953, and in 1962, the University of Michigan awarded him the Doctor of Laws degree.
Kennedy married Edna H. Clippert in 1914 and the two had six children (five girls, one boy). Edna died in 1946 and Charles Kennedy died in September 25, 1966.
Charles Stuart Kennedy papers consist of reports, correspondence, and agendas of meetings of the Board of Regents, the Workers Education Service, the American College of Surgeons and World War II; and photographs. The collection is comprised of three series: Board of Regents, Personal Materials, and Taiwan Material.
Subjects:
Adult education.; American College of Surgeons.; Detroit (Mich.); Kennedy, Charles Stuart, 1887-1966.; Physicians--Michigan--Detroit.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; Workers Education Service (University of Michigan); World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Airplanes.; Handicapped persons.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Kennedy, Charles Stuart, 1887-1966.; Nurses--Michigan.; Physicians--Michigan--Detroit.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; University of Puerto Rico.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Board of Regents
  The Board of Regents series includes agendas, reports, background materials, and correspondence from the meetings of the Regents, 1946 to 1961. There is also a smaller grouping of files relating to the University's Workers Education Service and the ensuing controversy which involved the Michigan Committee on Civil Rights.
  - Meeting files
    - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - January 1948-March 1950 (Box 2)
    - April 1950-February 1952 (Box 3)
    - March 1952-September 1953 (Box 4)
    - October 1953-March 1955 (Box 5)
    - April 1955-April 1956 (Box 6)
    - May 1956-March 1957 (Box 7)
    - April 1957-April 1958 (Box 8)
    - May 1958-September 1959 (Box 9)
    - September 1959-December 1960 (Box 10)
    - January-December 1961 (Box 11)
- Board
  The Personal series is small, with files that include a scattering of letters from Kennedy's time as Regent, letters from soldiers during World War II, letters of condolence, and documents regarding Kennedy's involvement as the lead surgeon presiding over Harry Houdini when Houdini died. Correspondence includes letters from baseball great Ty Cobb, Edgar Guest, and Madame Chaing Kai-shek. Kennedy's student notebooks from his studies at the University of Michigan are also found here. Also found in this series is Kennedy's Roy Bishop Canfield Memorial lecture and his address to the 1945 graduating class at Wayne State University.
  - Other University-related Material
    - Workers Education Service, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Workers Education Service, 5 folders (Box 12)
    - University Budget 1946-1947 (Box 12)
    - University Budget 1947-1948 (Box 12)
- Personal Materials
  - Biographical sketch (Box 12)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated (Box 12)
    - 1933 (Box 12)
    - 1940-1946 (Box 12)
    - 1946-1950 (Box 12)
    - 1951-1952 (Box 12)
    - 1953 (Box 12)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 12)
    - 1957-1964 (Box 12)
    - Concerning the American College of Surgeons 1943 (Box 12)
    - Letters of condolence received upon the death of his mother 1937 (Box 12)
    - Letters of condolence received by family members (Box 12)
    - Soldiers in World War II, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - Ty Cobb 1948-1957 (Box 12)
  - Documents Concerning Harry Houdini 1927 (Box 12)
  - Documents Concerning Time as Regent 1948-1962 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1947-1966 (Box 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings -- Ty Cobb (Box 12)
  - Photographs 1910-1956, undated (Box 12)
  - Publications (Box 12)
  - Student notebooks, University of Michigan, 6 volumes (Box 13)
- Taiwan Material
  The Taiwan Material folder contains three items that Kennedy received relating to his 1956 trip to Taiwan (Free China) as part of a University of Michigan delegation. The first piece is entitled "Old Rock Inscription" by Professor Tung-Tso-pin. The second piece says "Welcome to Free China" and is signed with names of the Chinese representatives that Kennedy's group met with. The final piece is made up of photographs of people from the group's trip including University of Michigan President Harlan Hatcher. Some additional material related to the trip is found in the personal series.
  - "Old Rock Inscription" (Folder UAl)
  - "Welcome to Free China," 1956 (Folder UAl)
  - Photographs of University of Michigan Delegation and Hosts 1956 (Folder UAl)